<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: design | P. Taylor Goetz]]></title>
  <link href="http://ptgoetz.github.io/blog/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ptgoetz.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-26T21:57:39-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ptgoetz.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[P. Taylor Goetz]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ptgoetz@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Sample Code Matters]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptgoetz.github.io/blog/2013/05/01/why-sample-code-matters/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-01T15:52:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptgoetz.github.io/blog/2013/05/01/why-sample-code-matters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whenever you write code samples for an API or library -- or even a blog post -- you should treat it as though you are writing the production guidance system for the space shuttle. Okay, that may be a little extreme, but you should at least make your best effort to ensure the code is error free and follows best practices. Why? Any bugs, vulnerabilities, anti-patterns, or cruft of any kind <strong><em>will replicate like drunken bunnies.</em></strong></p>

<p><img src="/images/lots-of-bunnies.gif" title="Can't hold their liquor." alt="Bunnies" /></p>

<p>In a blog post titled <a href="http://www.viva64.com/en/b/0199/">Why Windows 8 drivers are buggy</a> Andrey Karpov discusses what he found when performing static analysis on Windows 8 driver examples published by Microsoft. In short, those examples aren't exactly stellar. But they're just examples and aren't that important, right? I beg to differ.</p>

<p>In my opinion, the salient point of the article is best summarized in the following paragraph (emphasis mine):</p>

<blockquote><p>"<del>Bugs in samples are not that critical as bugs in real-life software.</del> Nevertheless, bugs can migrate from samples to real-life projects and cause developers a lot of troubles. Even within the Windows 8 Driver Samples pack we found identical bugs. The reason is obvious: copying-and-pasting a code fragment from a nearby sample. In the same way these errors will get into real-life drivers."</p></blockquote>

<p>In fact, I would rearrange that first sentence to read: <em>"Bugs in samples will become critical bugs in real-life software."</em></p>

<p>The evils of <em>copying-and-pasting</em> aside, the truth is that developers reading your sample code will likely (perhaps blindly) trust that a given example is the right way to do things. Like it or not, when writing examples you are acting as a teacher and can't make any assumptions about your pupils.</p>

<p>To illustrate how sample code can proliferate, consider <a href="https://github.com/nathanmarz/storm-starter/commit/91550313b5288e9c059165e6ce8bad180fb764cb#diff-e9057e0def4e5aa863bdc4a6fdb98fe3R42">this commit</a> to the <a href="">storm-starter project</a>. That was from two years ago, shortly after storm had been open-sourced. The impetus was to help people more familiar with java/Maven than clojure/Leiningen get started with storm. Since then, that code/comment has proliferated fairly far and wide, as can be seen from a <a href="https://www.google.com/#filter=0&amp;q=%22keep+storm+out+of+the+jar-with-dependencies%22">google search for "keep storm out of the jar-with-dependencies"</a>. In retrospect, I should have used the <a href="http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-shade-plugin/">maven shade plugin</a> instead, since it plays better with certain frameworks like Spring. Not a big deal, but the <del>cat</del> drunken bunny is out of the bag and on a love mission.</p>

<p>I'll admit that I'm in no way perfect in this respect. But I strive toward that goal and believe that all serious developers should as well.</p>

<p>Let's keep the drunken bunnies at bay. ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
